Finding Aid for Howard Bishop Lewis Papers, 1922-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Howard Bishop Lewis Papers 1922-1954
Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954.
851720 Aa 2
Papers of Howard Bishop Lewis (1887-1954), professor and chairman of the Department of Biological Chemistry at the University of Michigan (1922-1954), director of the College of Pharmacy at the University of Michigan (1933-1947), a supervisor for the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project, and an active participant in many professional organizations and policy committees especially concerning health and nutrition. The series in the collection are: Photographs; Writings; Administrative; Examinations; Lectures; Research Files; Correspondence; and Organizational Activities and Interests.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were transferred from the U-M Medical School (donor no. 647 )
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Howard Bishop Lewis was born in Southington, Connecticut on November 8, 1887. He received his bachelor of arts in 1908 and his Ph.D. in 1913 from Yale University. Lewis then worked as an instructor in physiological chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania until 1915, when he took a position as associate professor in physiological chemistry at the University of Illinois. He remained at Illinois until 1922, then accepted an appointment as chairman of the Department of Biological Chemistry at the University of Michigan. From 1933 to 1947 Lewis served as both chairman of the Department of Biological Chemistry and as the director of the College of Pharmacy. A series of strokes forced the Department to choose an acting chairman, Lewis' colleague Adam A. Christman, in the spring of 1953. Lewis died on March 7, 1954.
In addition to his administrative duties as chairman and dean, Lewis was also a professor in the Department of Biological Chemistry, teaching courses related to biological chemistry and nutrition. He was especially involved in the curriculum of graduate students. He also served on the supervising committee for the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project.
His research interest in nutrition prompted Lewis to become active in a number of nutritional and health organizations. Notably, he served as an officer in a few of these organizations. He was president of the Michigan Nutrition Committee/Council from 1948-1952. (The Committee was renamed the Council on November 26, 1946, as documented in Lewis' papers). For the American Institute of Nutrition, he served on the council during 1941-42, before he became vice-president of the group in 1943 and president in 1943-1944.
Because of his special interest in nutrition, Lewis was appointed to a number of national policy boards and committees that were deemed especially important during the war years. He was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1949, and served on the National Board of Medical Examiners from 1935 to 1950. From 1943 until his death, he also served on a number of National Research Council committees, which had a direct influence on national policy on nutrition in the 1940s leading to many food enrichment programs for milk and flour.
Besides his role in nutrition and health organizations, Lewis was active in many professional organizations of his field. He served as an active member for a number of national bodies, including the American Chemical Society, the American Medical Association, and the Great Lakes Research Institute. He served as officer for many groups as well. For the American Society of Biological Chemists, he served as secretary from 1929-1933, vice-president from 1933-1935, president from 1935-1937, and on the council from 1937-1940 and 1941-1942. He was also at one time president of the Michigan Academy of Arts, Science and Letters.
In addition to membership and acting as an officer, Lewis served the professional community through activity on several editorial boards. These include the journals for the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine from 1927-1938, Physiological Reviews from 1935-1939, the Journal of Nutrition from 1935-1945, Chemical Reviews from 1938-1940, and the Journal of Biological Chemistry from 1938-1954.
Because of his standing in the field of biochemistry, Lewis was called to serve on several committees to award professional recognition. These include the American Chemical Society's Eli Lilly Award and Borden Award, the American Institute of Nutrition's Borden Award, the Mead-Johnson Award, the American Medical Association's Goldburger Award, the American Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Award, and the Nutrition Foundation Award.
Adam A. Christman has written a more detailed biography of Lewis. This volume is catalogued separately.
The personal papers of Howard Bishop Lewis concern his public activities rather than his private life. This includes his roles as educator and administrator at the University, and as a researcher in the fields of health and nutrition. The materials have been divided into eight series: Photographs; Writings; Administrative; Examinations; Lectures; Research Files; Correspondence; and Organizational Activities and Interests.
Subjects:
Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954.; Medicine--Michigan.; Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Biochemistry--Research.; Michigan Nutrition Committee.; Nutrition--Research.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Photographs
  - Two portraits 1940s undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  Writings include several bibliographies of Lewis' published work. However, not all of his published work is listed. This series also contains a number of book reviews Lewis wrote for several different journals, and manuscripts of both published and unpublished work. Some of his published work, including laboratory manuals and the manuscripts included in this series, are separately catalogued.
  - Bibliographies 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews 1938-1953 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - Amino Acid Synthesis 1924 (Box 1)
    - Butylacetic Acid 1944 (Box 1)
    - "The Chemist and Biology" 1936 (Box 1)
    - "The Chemist and the World's Food Supply" 1932 (Box 1)
    - "The Chemist and the World's Food Supply (Revised)" 1936 (Box 1)
    - Creatinine Thesis 1919 (Box 1)
    - Hippuric Acid 1952 (Box 1)
    - Histidine, 195? (Box 1)
    - Mannitol (Box 1)
    - Metabolism of Sulfur 1928, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Natural Toxicants and Nutrition (Box 1)
    - Nutrition (Box 1)
    - Urocanic Acid 1942 (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series includes correspondence and general information on a number of concerns Lewis dealt with, including space allocation and supplies for the labs, faculty and student determinations, arranging non-resident lecturers, and curriculum changes. His role as chairman of the Department of Biological Chemistry in the Medical School also meant he served on a number of internal committees for both his Department and the School, especially those dealing with wartime staffing and inter-departmental curriculum cooperation. He was also one of the select few chosen to serve on the supervising committee of the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project, a group dedicated to studying and developing peaceful uses of nuclear energy.
  - Buildings and Supplies
    - Apparatus (Box 1)
    - Chemicals (Box 1)
    - Building Alterations 1936-1939 (Box 1)
    - Buildings and Grounds Department 1936-1950 (Box 1)
    - Library Acquisitions (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Cooperation with Educational Institutions Committee 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - Cooperation with Educational Institutions Committee 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    - Cooperation with Educational Institutions Committee 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - Cooperation with Educational Institutions Committee 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Health Sciences Subcommittee on Faculty Research Fund 1943-1949 (Box 1)
    - Health Sciences Subcommittee on Nutrition 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - Medical School Committee on Research 1945 (Box 1)
    - Medical School Committee on Hospital Laboratories 1940 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters 1938-1946 (Box 1)
    - Occupational Deferment Committee (Box 1)
  - Curriculum
    - Combined Curriculum in Medicine and Letters 1944-1948 (Box 1)
    - Comprehensive Examinations Committee 1928 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Medicine Program 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Postgraduate Decentralized Resident Training Program 1948-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Postgraduate Preclinical Science 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Technicians' Committee 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Faculty
    - Biochemistry Department Newsletter 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Pharmacology Appointment 1941 (Box 1)
    - Policies on Armed Forces Commissions 1942-1950 (Box 1)
    - Recommendations 1925-1935 (Box 1)
  - Medical School Reports
    - Annual Report of the Dean 1936-1944, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Report on Medical Education 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Phoenix Project
    - Cancer Research Survey 1951 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation Presentation 1950 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation Presentation Supplements 1950 (Box 2)
    - General 1948 (Box 2)
    - General 1949 (Box 2)
    - General 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - General 1951 (Box 2)
    - General 1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Grant Applications April 1952 (Box 2)
    - Grant Applications November 1952 (Box 2)
    - Laboratory Expansion Project 1951 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1948-1953, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Nash-Kelvinator Grant 1951-1953 (Box 2)
    - Preliminary Planning Committee 1951 (Box 2)
  - Students
    - Graduate Student Service Deferments, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
    - Student Evaluations 1938-1953 (Box 2)
  - Visiting Lecturers 1947-1954 (Box 2)
- Examinations
  Examinations, shows in part Lewis' time spent as an educator. The examinations include small quizzes up to doctoral level competency exams for a number of years.
  - 1931-1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934-1935, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 2)
- Lectures
  Lectures also shows Lewis' role as an educator. A few of the lectures contained in the Undated folder are notes from his classroom lectures. Other lectures in the series include those he delivered at various conferences and commemoratory events, as well as the speech he gave in 1948 when he was named the Henry Russel Lecturer at the University. The topics of the lectures largely concern his research interests in nutrition and proteins.
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - 1941-1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - 1946 (Box 2)
  - 1947 (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - 1951 (Box 3)
  - 1952 (Box 3)
- Research Files
  Research Files cover a number of Lewis' research interests and are organized by topic. These largely include drafts of articles, published articles and correspondence that Lewis collected, authored by himself and others. Most of the material is annotated by Lewis, and shows what he found applicable to his own research.
  - Biological Chemistry Department Research Projects (Box 3)
  - Biological Methylatum (Box 3)
  - Branched Chain Acids 1948 (Box 3)
  - Calcium in Blood Serum 1937 (Box 3)
  - Desaminocasein 1946 (Box 3)
  - Enriched Bread and Flour 1943-1947 (Box 3)
  - Gas Warfare (Box 3)
  - Gelatine 1945 (Box 3)
  - Gliadin 1937 (Box 3)
  - Gluconolactone 1939-1943 (Box 3)
  - Hair 1933-1936 (Box 3)
  - Hippuric Acid (Box 3)
  - Histidine 1941 (Box 3)
  - Illinois Method for Determining Protein Value (Box 3)
  - Keratins (Hair and Skin) 1940 (Box 3)
  - Oleomargarine (Box 3)
  - Pathology Reports 1926-1946, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Preparations (Box 3)
  - Rackham Arthritis Research Unit 1947 (Box 3)
  - Rutgers Protein Conference 1949 (Box 3)
  - Selenium 1937 (Box 3)
  - Silk Proteins 1934 (Box 3)
  - Skin Pigmentation 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - Species Evolution 1939 (Box 3)
  - Topical Bibliographies, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence is alphabetized by the author's last name, through the first two letters. Most of correspondence has a copy of Lewis' response attached. The correspondence largely covers his public interests, including letters written as a function of his administrative duties to his Department and the Medical School deans, as well as letters written to peers concerning contemporary research. There is no personal correspondence to his family.
  - A (Box 3)
  - Adolph, William H. (Box 3)
  - Albagli, Benjamin (Box 3)
  - Andrews, James (Box 3)
  - Autographs, A-K (Box 3)
  - Autographs, L-Z (Box 3)
  - Ba (Box 3)
  - Be (Box 3)
  - Bh-Bl (Box 3)
  - Bo (Box 3)
  - Br-By (Box 4)
  - Bausch and Lomb (Box 4)
  - Beach, Eliot F. (Box 4)
  - Beazley, Charles (Box 4)
  - Borden Company (Box 4)
  - Brand, Erwin, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Ca (Box 4)
  - Ch (Box 4)
  - Cl (Box 4)
  - Co (Box 4)
  - Cr-Cu (Box 4)
  - Cabot, Hugh (Box 4)
  - Cannon, Paul R. (Box 4)
  - Chemical Rubber Company (Box 4)
  - Christian Becker Inc. (Box 4)
  - Da-Do (Box 4)
  - Dr-Dy (Box 4)
  - Doisy, Edward A. (Box 4)
  - Fa-Fi (Box 4)
  - Fl-Fu (Box 4)
  - Furstenberg, Albert Carl (Box 4)
  - Ga-Gi (Box 4)
  - Go (Box 4)
  - Gr-Gu (Box 4)
  - Gaebler, Oliver H. (Box 4)
  - Griffith, Wendell H. (Box 4)
  - Ha (Box 4)
  - He-Hi (Box 4)
  - Ho (Box 4)
  - Hu-Hy (Box 4)
  - Hammett, Frederick S. (Box 4)
  - Hoobler, Icie Macy (Box 4)
  - Hubbell, Rebecca (Box 4)
  - Hughes, Josiah Simpson (Box 4)
  - I (Box 4)
  - J (Box 4)
  - Johnson, Treat (Box 4)
  - Ka-Ki (Box 4)
  - Kl-Ku (Box 5)
  - Kyker, Granvil Charles (Box 5)
  - La-Le (Box 5)
  - Li-Ly (Box 5)
  - Langley, Wilson D. (Box 5)
  - Lewis, Howard Bishop (Personal) (Box 5)
  - Luck, Murray J. (Box 5)
  - Ma, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Mc (Box 5)
  - Me (Box 5)
  - Mi-My (Box 5)
  - Mattill, Henry A. 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Mattill, Henry A. 1940-1953 (Box 5)
  - McMillan Company (Box 5)
  - Merck and Company Inc. (Box 5)
  - N (Box 5)
  - Nelson, Erwin E. (Box 5)
  - O (Box 5)
  - Pa-Pf (Box 5)
  - Ph-Pu (Box 5)
  - Parke-Davis and Company (Box 5)
  - Q (Box 5)
  - Ra-Ri (Box 5)
  - Ro-Ru (Box 5)
  - Robinson, Charles S. (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 5)
    (includes photographs of department labs)
  - Rose, William C. (Box 5)
  - S-Se (Box 5)
  - Sh-So (Box 5)
  - St-Sz (Box 5)
  - Sahyun, Melville (Box 5)
  - Smith, Arthur H. (Box 5)
  - Stearns, Genevieve (Box 5)
  - Sullivan, Michael X. (Box 5)
  - T 1936 (Box 5)
  - Tennant, Chauncey E. (Box 5)
  - Tucker, Helen F. (Box 5)
  - U (Box 6)
  - University of California Visiting Professor, Spring 1953 (Box 6)
  - V 1936-1938 (Box 6)
  - Venkataraman, Alamela (Box 6)
  - Venkataraman, P.R. (Box 6)
  - Wa-Wh (Box 6)
  - Wi (Box 6)
  - Wo-Wy (Box 6)
  - W.B. Saunders Company (Box 6)
  - White, Julius (Box 6)
  - Wiley, Frank S. 1935-1938 (Box 6)
  - Williams and Wilkins Company (Box 6)
  - XYZ 1936 (Box 6)
- Organizational Activities and Interests
  Organizational Activities and Interests documents Lewis' roles in various professional organizations and national policy boards and committees. The series also contains material related to the various editorial boards and awards committees he served on.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science
    - Gordon Conference 1950 (Box 6)
    - Symposium December 1952 (Box 6)
  - American Chemical Society
    - Borden Award 1942-1944 (Box 6)
    - Eli Lilly Award 1950-1951 (Box 6)
    - General (Box 6)
    - Journal of ACS (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Section 1950 (Box 6)
  - American Institute of Nutrition
    - Borden Award 1943-1954 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Professional Nutrition 1945-1946 (Box 6)
    - Mead Johnson and Company Award 1938-1943 (Box 6)
  - American Medical Association 1940-1953
    - Council on Foods and Nutrition 1940-1953, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Council on Milk Fortification 1948 (Box 6)
    - Council on Pharmacy and Chemistry 1946-1952 (Box 6)
    - Goldberger Award 1949-1952 (Box 6)
    - Journal of AMA 1950 (Box 6)
    - Nutrition Foundation Awards 1948 (Box 6)
  - American Pharmaceutical Manufacturers' Association
    - General 1949-1952 (Box 7)
  - American Pharmaceutical Manufacturers' Association
    - Award 1941 (Box 7)
  - American Physiological Society 1950-1953
    - General (Box 7)
  - American Society of Biological Chemists 1946-1952
    - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology
      - Meeting 1950-1953, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Placement Service 1946-1952 (Box 7)
    - General 1946-1952 (Box 7)
    - Journal of Biological Chemistry 1946-1952
      - Editorial Board Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Editorial Board Yearly Reports (Box 7)
    - Nominating Committee 1951-1952 (Box 7)
    - Training of Professional Biochemists 1948-1951 (Box 7)
  - Army Medical Center 1947-1953
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - General (Box 7)
  - Arthritis and Rheumatism Foundation 1949-1952 (Box 7)
  - Association of Medical Colleges 1952-1953 (Box 7)
  - Children's Fund of Michigan 1942-1947 (Box 7)
  - Great Lakes Research Institute 1944-1952 (Box 7)
  - Lunch Club 1939-1951, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters 1948-1953 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Department of Health Commissioner's Nutrition Advisory Committee 1950-1952 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Rural Health Conference 1948-1952 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State Hospital Commission Project 1944-1945 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State Medical Society 1949-1951 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Nutrition Committee 1940-1952
    - Constitution and Minutes 1947-1951 (Box 7)
    - General (Box 7)
    - Membership (Box 7)
    - Monthly Reports 1943-1945 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Enrichment 1945-1952, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Washington Group 1945-1948 (Box 8)
  - National Academy of Sciences
    - Election Correspondence 1949 (Box 8)
    - General 1949-1953, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - National Dairy Council Subcommittee on Milk Protein
    - Contracts 1947-1949 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence1947-1951 (Box 8)
    - Nutrition Foundation Grant 1946-1953 (Box 8)
  - National Institutes of Health
    - General 1949-1953, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Grant 1952-1954 (Box 8)
  - National Research Council
    - Committee on Effect of Heat on Proteins 1943 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Foods and Proteins 1948-1951 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Food Consumption 1944 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Growth 1949 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Nomenclature 1947-1950 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Protein Foods 1947-1948 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Proteins 1943-1945 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1949-1953 (Box 8)
    - Division of Biology and Agriculture 1950 (Box 8)
    - Fellowship Awards Committee 1951-1953 (Box 8)
    - NRC Handbook Committee on Sulfur 1949-1953 (Box 8)